<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesties gracious speech to both Houses of Parlaiment [sic]: together with the L. Chancellors, in Christ-Church-Hall in Oxford, on Tuesday, October 10. 1665.</title>
            <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02077</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3053A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171222</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47012344</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47012344</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174310</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02077)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174310)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2683:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesties gracious speech to both Houses of Parlaiment [sic]: together with the L. Chancellors, in Christ-Church-Hall in Oxford, on Tuesday, October 10. 1665.</title>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
                  <author>Clarendon, Edward Hyde, Earl of, 1609-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Stephen Bulkley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Re-printed at York, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Columbia University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174310:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>His Majeſties GRACIOUS SPEECH to both Houſes of PARLAIMENT: Together with the L. Chancellors, In <hi>Chriſt-Church-Hall</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> On <hi>Tueſday, October</hi> 10. 1665.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Re-Printed at <hi>York</hi> by <hi>Stephen Bulkley,</hi> 1665.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:174310:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:174310:2"/>
            <head>HIS MAJESTIES GRACIOUS SPEECH To both HOUSES of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am confident you all believe, that if it had not been abſolutely neceſſary to conſult with you, I would not have called you together at this time, when the Contagion hath ſo ſpread it ſelf over ſo many parts of the Kingdom. I take it for a good Omen to ſee ſo good an appearance this day, and I doubt not, every day will add to your num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and I give you all My thanks for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance ſo far with My deſires.</p>
            <p>The truth is, as I entred upon this War by your advice and encouragement; ſo I do deſire, that you may as frequently as is poſſible, receive informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Conduct, and Effects of it, and that I may have the continuance of your chearfull Supply for the carrying it on. I will not deny to you, that it hath proved more chargeable then I could ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine it would have been: The addition they ſtill made to their Fleets, beyond their firſt purpoſe, made it unavoidably neceſſary for me to make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable Preparations, which God hath hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bleſſed with ſucceſs in all Encounters. And as the Enemy have uſed their utmoſt endevours by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174310:3"/>Calumnies and falſe ſuggeſtions, to make themſelves Friends, and to perſwade others to aſſiſt them againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s; ſo I have not been wanting to encourage thoſe Princes who have been wronged by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> to recover their own by force; and in order thereunto, have aſſiſted the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi> with a very great ſum of ready Money, and am to continue a ſupply to him, who is now in the bowels of their Country with a Powerfull Army.</p>
            <p>Theſe Iſſues, which I may tell you, have been made with very good Conduct and Husbandry, (nor indeed doe I know that any thing hath been ſpent, that could have been well and fafely ſaved) I ſay, this expence will not ſuffer you to wonder, that the great Supply which you gave me for this War, in ſo bountifull a proportion, is upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter already ſpent: So that I muſt not onely expect an aſſiſtance from you, to carry on this War; but ſuch an aſſiſtance, as may inable Me to defend My Self and you, againſt a more Powerfull Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, if he ſhall prefer the Frienaſhip of the <hi>Dutch</hi> before Mine.</p>
            <p>I told you, when I entred upon this War, That I had not ſuch a Brutal appetite, as to make War for War ſake. I am ſtill of the ſame mind: I have been ready to receive any Propoſitions that <hi>France</hi> hath thought fit to offer to that end: but hitherto nothing hath been offered worthy My acceptance; nor is the <hi>Dutch</hi> leſs inſolent, though I know no advantage they have had, but the continuance of the Contagion: God Almighty, I hope, will ſhortly deprive them of that encouragement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Chancellour will inform you of all the Particulars.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:174310:3"/>
            <head>The <hi>LORD CHANCELLOR'S</hi> SPEECH To both HOUSES of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords, and you the Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes of the Houſe of Commons.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He King is not content, you ſee, to leave you to your ſelves to make a ſtare of this War, and the ſucceſs that hath attended it, by your own obſervation, and the general Communication of all that hath fallen out, which in truth hath left few men ignorant of any thing, who have had any curioſity to inform themſelves; but takes care that you be informed by Himſelf, that you may know all that he knows, that ſo you may be able to give Him your Counſel upon the cleareſt evidence.</p>
            <p>In order to this, it will not I hope be unſeaſonable or ingrateful to you, to refreſh your memory, by looking ſome years backwards, even to the time of His Majeſties happy Reſtauration, that we may take the better proſpect of the poſture we are now in, and how we have come into it.</p>
            <p>What inclinations His Majeſty brought home with Him, to live in Amity with His Neighbours of <hi>Holland,</hi> though He had received In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities enough from them, and in truth had been little leſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed there, than He had been in <hi>England;</hi> needs no other manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, than that He choſe that place to imbarque Himſelf in, when He was preſſed by the two Neighbour Kings, from whom He had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived more civilities, to have made uſe of their Ports. It cannot be denied, but that His reception in <hi>Holland</hi> was with great civility and luſtre, and a ſufficient evidence that they had a full ſenſe of the high Honour His Majeſty had vouchſafed to them, and the departure from thence was with equal and mutual ſatisfaction in each other; which made many men the more to wonder, that albeit the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors who were to follow, had been nominated before the King left the <hi>Hague,</hi> there was ſo long an Interval before their Arrival here, that the two Neighbour Kings, and many other Princes had finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Ambaſſies of Congratulation, before we had heard any more from the United Provinces.</p>
            <p>You all remember how long it was before the Armies were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded, and the Fleets paid off; during which time, His Majeſty li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon his Credit, and eaſily contracted a great Debt for the meer
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174310:4"/>ſupport of himſelf and his houſhold, which was not ſo eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged afterwards. There was one thing that exceedingly ſurprized him, when he found (which will be incredible to poſterity) that a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Nation, uhat had made it ſelf terrible to Chriſtendom, by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fought more Battels than all the Neighbour Kingdoms and States together had ever done in ſo few years, and ſeemed to be in a poſture ready to fight them over again; that had ſo long Reigned over the Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an in formidable Fleets; ſhould at the time of his Majeſties happy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, as if on the ſudden all their Arms had been turned into Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhares, and their Swords into Pruning books, not have in all their Magazines, in all the Stores, Arms enough to put into the hands of five thouſand men, nor Proviſions enough to ſet out Ten new Ships to Sea. Which his Majeſty did not deſire ſhould be known to his beſt Neighbours, how little ſoever he ſuſpected their Affections; nor did indeed ſo much as make it known to his Parliament, but made it his firſt care, without the leaſt noiſe, and with all imaginable ſhifts, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the full ſupply of thoſe important Magazines and Stores which have been ever ſince repleniſhed as they ought to be.</p>
            <p>He had not the leaſt imagination that any of his Neighbours would wantonly affect to interrupt the happy Calm that he and themſelves enjoyed; and therefore reſolved to retrench the vaſt expence of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy; under which he found the Nation even to groan; and out of that good husbandry to provide for more neceſſary Disburſ ments: Yet, that the World might not think that he had abandoned the Ocean, and that the memory of the glorious Actions the Engliſh had ſo lately perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med upon it, might not vaniſh in an inſtant, after he had provided ſuch a Guard as the Narrow Seas never ought to be without, in the Spring he ſent a ſtrong Fleet againſt the Pirates of <hi>Algiers</hi> and <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poly</hi> (who had grown to that ſtrength and boldneſs, that they interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the whole Trade of Chriſtendom) as the only Enemies he would chooſe to have.</p>
            <p>It was a Deſign of great Glory, and equal Expence, crowned in the end by God Almighty, with the Succeſs we could wiſh, and with an entire ſubmiſſion to the Engliſh Flag, and as great ſecurity to all His Majeſties Subjects in their Trade, as the engagement and honour of Infidels can give; and this Agreement ratified with all formality (the like whereof had never been before) by the <hi>Great Turk</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the King again renewed his reſolution for a further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchment of his Naval expence, even to the leſſening of the Guard in the Narrow Seas; His Merchants in all places receiving leſs inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in their Trade, then they had in any former time undergone: until he received Intelligence from the <hi>Straights,</hi> that the faithleſs People of <hi>Algiers,</hi> who had ſo lately ſubmitted to him, had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted new Inſolencies upon ſome of his Subjects, or rather upon Foreign perſons taken by his Subjects into their poſſeſſion, and which the <hi>Turks</hi> pretended they might do without violation of the Treaty: But his Majeſty reſolving to admit none of thoſe Elucidations, loſt no time in ſending a new ſtrong Fleet into the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> to chaſtiſe thoſe perfidious Pirates; and after a chargeable War made upon them for near or full twelve Months, and after having taken
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174310:4"/>ſeveral of their Ships from them, and upon the matter blocking them up in their Harbours, He received a ſecond ſubmiſſion from them with better and more advantagious Conditions than the former.</p>
            <p>I muſt not omit one circumſtance; That about this time, the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who received much more prejudice and damage from the <hi>Turks</hi> than the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had done, beſought his Majeſty that he would once more ſend a Fleet into thoſe Seas againſt thoſe Pirates, and that it might upon all occaſions joyn with one they were likewiſe ready to ſend our to the ſame Chriſtian end, and for the utter extirpation of thoſe Sea-Robbers; and within a very ſhort time after the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet was gone, they likewiſe ſent <hi>De Ruyter</hi> with a good Fleet thither, which was ſo far from any conjunction with us, that when our ſhips chaſed any <hi>Algier-men</hi> near them, they never offered to obſtruct their flight, but quickly made it manifeſt, that they rather brought money with them to buy a diſhonourable and diſadvantagious Peace, than to make a War upon them.</p>
            <p>Matters ſtanding thus; The Kings Fleet being gone into the Straights againſt the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Pirates, and there remaining few ſhips in the Narrow Seas; we began every day to hear of Depredations by the <hi>Dutch</hi> upon our Merchants in all parts. Inſtead of delivering up the Iſland of <hi>Poleroon</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> (as by the Treaty they ought to have done) They by their Naval Power in thoſe parts hindered us from Trading there, and would not ſuffer our Ships to take in their Lading of ſuch Merchandiſe as the Factors had provided and made ready for their Fraight, upon pretence that thoſe parts where the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe was ready to be imbarqued, were in the Dominions of ſome Princes whom they had declared to be their Enemies, and ſo they would not ſuffer any Traffique to be maintained with them. And they publiſhed the like Declaration, and challenged the ſame Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty in <hi>Africa,</hi> and by vertue thereof would not ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r our ſhips to Trade upon that Coaſt, where we had a trade long before the <hi>Dutch</hi> had any footing in thoſe parts.</p>
            <p>Theſe Inſolencies made that noiſe in the world, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants felt the effects of it in all places, till it reached the ears of the Parliament, which in <hi>April</hi> was twelve months, preſented the ſame to his Majeſty, and beſought him that he would take ſome ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and effectual courſe for the redreſs of thoſe wrongs, diſhonours, and Indignities, which were the greateſt Obſtructions of our Trade; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that in the proſecution thereof they would with their Lives and Fortunes aſſiſt his Majeſty againſt all oppoſitions whatſoever.</p>
            <p>My Lords and Gentlemen, You very well remember, that though His Majeſty was very well pleaſed with the great Zeal you ſhewed for the advancement of Trade, He was far from reſolving to make a War upon the warmth of that Declaration, but told you that he would examine and peruſe the particular Complaints which had been repreſented to his Parliament, and would thereupon demand juſtice and reparation from the <hi>States-General;</hi> which Demand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e appointed his Miniſter reſiding there, to make in a ſhort time after. What ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that Candid way of proceeding found, is enough known to the world. Inſtead of other application, they declare themſelves wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully offended with the Declaration of the Parliament, with many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoleng
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174310:5"/>expreſſions ſuitable to the manners of a Common-wealth; They gave preſent Orders for equipping a very great Fleet, and the raiſing many Land-Souldiers, making greater preparations for VVar, than they had done in many years before. They had made a complaint to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, that a Captain of one of the ſhips which his Majeſty had lent to the Royal Company, had in his Voyage thither, taken a Fort be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them neer <hi>Cape verte,</hi> for which they demanded ſatisfaction. The King aſſured them, that he had not the leaſt Commiſſion or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from him for ſo doing; that He expected him home very ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, and then he ſhould be ſure to undergo that puniſhment which the nature of his offence required, when the matter ſhould be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and they ſhould be ſure to receive full reparation. This ſatisfied them not, but in great fury they reſolve to ſend forthwith a ſtrong Fleet to <hi>Guiny,</hi> and granted a Commiſſion (which they took care to publiſh) to the Commander in chief, to make war upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in thoſe parts, and to do them all the miſchief they could.</p>
            <p>The King found himſelf now obliged, in what ſtrait ſoever, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the protection of his Subjects in thoſe parts, and for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of that trade, which I doubt is not enough taken to heart, and the value thereof not enough underſtood; and in order thereunto, with great ſpeed cauſed a Fleet to be made ready for that Expedition, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Command of his Highneſs Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> who was under ſail for the Voyage; when his Majeſty found it neceſſary to ſtop the Prince his further proſecution of it, upon good intelligence that the <hi>Dutch</hi> had appointed their Admiral with a Fleet of fifty Sail, to convey the other Fleet deſigned for <hi>Guiny</hi> through the Channel in contempt of his Majeſty, who had a very ſmall Fleet in readineſs; and that <hi>De Ruyter</hi> was likewiſe ſent out of the <hi>Straights</hi> from proſecuting the <hi>Turks,</hi> to make war upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>Guiny,</hi> when at the ſame time they had earneſtly preſſed the King upon many profeſſions of deſire to prevent a war, that Prince <hi>Rupert's</hi> Fleet might ſtay in Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, as theirs ſhould do, till ſome means might be found for an accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation of all Differences. And in truth, this very difficult Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem of pretending one thing, and intending another; of promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with all ſolemnity, and never reſolving to perform; of ſwearing this day not to do a thing, when they had ſerved their turn by having done it yeſterday, that no body could know, is the higheſt Pinacle of their Wiſdome of State, by which they govern their affairs, and delude their Neighbours.</p>
            <p>The Winds were not favourable to this triumphant deſign: And now the <hi>King</hi> found the value of the Vote, and Declaration of His Parliament, it was a Rich and a Maſſie Vote, which in a ſhort time He coined into Two hundred thouſand pounds ready money in the Chamber of the City of <hi>London;</hi> with which he gave Order forthwith to make ready more Ships; and the <hi>Duke</hi> going Himſelf to the Fleet, by His indefatigable induſtry, with incredible Expedition added ſo many good Ships to thoſe under the Command of Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> that in <hi>November</hi> He put Himſelf on Board the Fleet, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to ſtop the <hi>Dutch</hi> if the Wind gave them leave to purſue their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Reſolution, which from the time the Duke was known to be at Sea, <hi>they</hi> fairly declined, and were content rather to be ſafe in <hi>their</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:174310:5"/>own Harbours, than to look to the ſecurity of their Merchants; It was high time now to ſeiz upon as many of their ſhips as came in out way, to ſatisfie the Damages we had reaſon to believe we ſhould ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from <hi>De Ruyter</hi>'s Expedition into <hi>Guiny</hi> with the Commiſſion mentioned before: but there was not the Lading of one ſhip ſold or diſpoſed of, till His Majeſty received full information of <hi>De Ruyters</hi> having begun the War upon the Coaſt of <hi>Africa,</hi> by ſeizing upon our ſhips, taking our Forts, and committing all the acts of Hoſtility, which his Commiſſion directed him unto; His Majeſty likewiſe at the ſame time receiving new Advertiſement of their refuſal to deliver up the Iſland of <hi>Poleroon</hi> to him, which they were bound to by their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And will you nor wonder after all this at the confidence of theſe men? and more, that any Neighbour Prince ſhould have that confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in them, as to declare, that the King our Maſter is the Aggreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, that he firſt began the War?</p>
            <p>From this time the War began to be more in earneſt, and to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on at another Expence. Though his Royal Highneſs ventured himſelf in <hi>November,</hi> in a Fleet conſiſting of little more than fifty ſhips, to ſtop the <hi>Dutch</hi> from paſſing through the Channel; Yet in <hi>April</hi> (which was within few daies after your Prorogation, and the end of your laſt Seſſion) he went again to Sea with a much ſtronger Fleet, and more proportionate to the great preparations the Enemy had made; and even after he was gone to Sea, upon great additions of ſtrength every day made by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> more good ſhips were ſent to reinforce the Fleet, inſomuch, as upon that glorious third of <hi>June,</hi> when they had the courage to viſit our Coaſts, after the Duke had in vain called upon them at their own doors, and took many of their Merchants Ships in their fight, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet conſiſted of very few leſs than One hundred Sail. The Action and the Bleſſing of that day, hath been celebrated in all the Churches in <hi>England,</hi> and in the hearty devotions of all true <hi>Engliſh</hi> men; and therefore I ſhall no more of it here; ſave only, that whether the publick Joy then, even upon the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Thanksgiving day, was ſuperior to the Univerſal conſternation that ſpread it ſelf over the Nation before, I appeal to the breaſts of al here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: We who had the honour to be near the King at that time, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved him to be in that agony that cannot be expreſſed, an agony him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf could not have long endured, even when by all the intelligence he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived hourly from the Coaſt, he had reaſon to aſſure himſelf of the Victory. In that great Action we ſunk, burned and took eighteen good ſhips of war, whereof half were the beſt they had, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the loſs of one ſingle ſmall ſhip of ours, but of many noble and gallant Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, of too much value to be ventured (if there had not been a greater Venture) againſt ſuch traſh: and whoſe memories ought ever to be preſerved and extolled, and made precious to poſterity.</p>
            <p>No diligence was omitted, but all imaginable Expedition uſed in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing, repairing, and ſetting out the Fleet again; In order to which; the <hi>King</hi> himſelf made a journey thither, and ſtayed till he ſaw all teady and fit to Sail: but then, no entreaty, no importunity, could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with Him to venture his Brother again; though His Family and all preparations for the Voyage were ſtill on Board. His Majeſty too well remembred, and ſtill felt the impreſſions he had undergone the Third of <hi>June;</hi> and having got his Brother into his arms again; he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174310:6"/>would not return without him, committing the charge of the Fleet to the Earl of <hi>Sandwich,</hi> who had acted ſo good a part in it.</p>
            <p>Within few daies after, the beginning of <hi>July,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Sandwich</hi> went again to the Coaſt of <hi>Holland,</hi> with a Fleet in no degree inferior to the former, and Rode before the <hi>Texel</hi> to invite the <hi>Dutch</hi> to a new Engagement, they having uſed all the Arts at home to conceal the loſs and diſhonour they had undergone, and pretended to be very ready and ſolicitous for another Battel, when there was no appearance of their purpoſe to come out: And upon ſure intelligence that the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Fleet was coming about by the North, he received Orders to go for <hi>Norway,</hi> upon ſuch encouragement as was not made good, ſo that he was diſappointed of the expectation he had very reaſonably car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with him thither, and at a ſeaſon when that Climate gives little encouragement to abide in thoſe Seas. I am not yet to enlarge upon that matter, till I hear a better account from ſome of our friends: however though he could not meet with their whole Fleet, as he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to do; yet he hath had the good Forrune in two Encounters to take Eight of their great Ships of War, two of their beſt <hi>Eaſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> Ships, and about twenty of their Merchants ſhips, all under the protection of their Fleet, or ought to have been; and was then by Tempeſt, and other Reaſons, which no wiſdome of his could prevent, obliged to put into our own Harbours.</p>
            <p>I do not mention the great numbers of the Priſoners we have taken, an Army of Priſoners, who, in truth do us more harm at Land, than ever they did at Sea, and are a charge that never fell under our Eſtimate and computation: I would not be underſtood, that we had entred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a War, and never thought of Priſoners, and ſick, and wounded men; but, that the Priſoners, and wounded men ſhould bring upon us ſo prodigious an Expence, and of which we can yet ſee no bottom; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, as in one place, I think <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> that charge comes to twelve hundred pounds the week; I ſay, ſuch an Expence never came into our computation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> tells you, He hath enabled the Prince and Biſhop of <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> to demand Juſtice from thoſe who have ſo notoriouſly oppreſſed him with ſuch outragious Circumſtances of Inſolence and ſcorn, as are enough known to the world; and he hath demanded it bravely, in ſuch an Equipage as hath not been made for little Money, in which he can take, as well as ask, ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>After all this, ſince there is a Juſtice due to the worſt Enemies, We muſt do them this right, that they do not at all ſeem weary of the War, they do not diſcover the leaſt inclination to Peace. It is true, the <hi>French King</hi> hath offered his Mediation: and truly if he intends no more than a Mediation, it is an Office very worthy <hi>The moſt Chriſtian King;</hi> I wiſh with all my heart, that (as a Mediatour) he would make equal propoſitions, or that he would not ſo importunately preſs His Majeſty to conſent to thoſe he makes, upon an Inſtance and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that he holds himſelf engaged by a former Treaty (of which we never heard till ſince the beginning of this war, and had ſome reaſon to have preſumed the contrary) to aſſiſt the <hi>Dutch</hi> with Men and Money, if His Majeſty doth not conſent.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty tells you, that he hath not an appetite to make war for war ſake, but will be alwaies ready to make ſuch a Peace as may
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174310:6"/>be for His Honour, and the intereſt of his Subjects; and no doubt but it will be a great trouble and grief to him to find ſo great a Prince, towards whom he hath manifeſted ſo great an affection, in conjunction with his Enemies: yet even the apprehenſion of ſuch a war will not terrifie him to purchaſe a Peace by ſuch Conceſſions as he would be aſhamed to make you acquainted with; of which nature you will eaſily believe the Propoſitions hitherto made to be, when you know that the releaſe of <hi>Poleroon</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> and the demoliſhing the Fort of <hi>Cabo-Corſo</hi> upon the Coaſt of <hi>Guiny,</hi> are two, which would be upon the matter to be content with a very vile Trade in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> under their Comptroll, and with none in <hi>Guiny.</hi> And yet theſe are not Propoſitions unreaſonable enough to pleaſe the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who reproach <hi>France</hi> for interpoſing for Peace, inſtead of aſſiſting them in the War; boldly inſiſting upon the advantage the Contagion in <hi>London</hi> and ſome other parts of the Kingdome gives them, by which they confidently ſay, the <hi>King</hi> will be no longer able to maintain a Fleet againſt them at Sea; and as if God Almighty had ſent this heavy viſitation upon the <hi>Kingdom</hi> on their behalf, and to expoſe it to their malice and inſolence. They load us with ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, as the civility of no other Language will admit the Relation; the truth is, they have a Dialect of rudeneſs ſo peculiar to their Language and their People, that it is high time for all <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> to oblige them to ſome Reformation, if they intend to hold Correſpondence or Commerce with them,</p>
            <p>My Lords and Gentlemen, You ſee in what poſture we ſtand with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to our Neighbours abroad, who are our declared Enemies; their malice and activity to make others declare themſelves ſo too; the great preparations they make, and even Declarations that they will have another Battel, towards which they have in readineſs an equal number of new, greater, and better ſhips to thoſe they have loſt, furniſhed with larger and greater Artillery; ſo that if they were to be manned with any other Nation then their own, they might be worthy our apprehenſion. What preparations are to be made on our part, you can beſt judge. I have fully obeyed the Command that was laid upon me, in making you this plain, clear, true narrative of what hath paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; I have no Order to make any refliction upon it, nor any deduction from it: The King himſelf hath told you, that the noble unparalleld Supply you have already given him, is upon the matter ſpent, ſpent with all the Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions of good Husbandry, that the nature of the affair would bear, What is more to be done, He leaves entirely to your own Generous underſtanding, being not more aſſured of any thing that is to come in this world, than that the ſame Noble indignation for the honour of the King and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that firſt provoked you to enflame the King himſelf, will continue the ſame paſſion ſtill boiling in your Loyal Breaſts, that all the world may ſee, which they hoped never to have ſeen, that never Prince and People were ſo entirely united in their Affections, for their true, joynt, inſeparable Honour, as the only ſure infallible Expedient to preſerve their diſtinct ſeveral Intereſt.</p>
            <p>My Lords and Gentlemen, you have great reaſon to be weary; yet having only preſented you a ſhort view of your Forreign Eremies, it may not be altogether unſeaſonable that you take a little proſpect of thoſe at home, thoſe unquiet, reſtleſs Spirits in your own Bowels, upon whoſe Infidelity I doubt your Enemies abroad have more dependence than upon their own Fleets. I muſt appeal to every one of your Obſervations, wherher the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances of thoſe men have not appeared to you more crected, more inſolent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174310:7"/>in all places fince the beginning of this war, then they were before; in what readineſs they were, if any misfortune had befallen the Kings Fleet (which they promiſed themſelves) to have brought the Calamity into your Fields, and into your Houſes, is notorioſly known. The horrid Murtherers of Our late Royal Maſter, have been received into the moſt ſecret Councels in <hi>Holland;</hi> and other infamous proſtituted perſons of our Nation, are admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a ſhare in the Conduct of their Affairs, and maintain their Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence here upon liberal allowances and Penſions. Too many of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Subjects, who were lent by this Crown to aſſiſt and defend this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful State againſt their Enemies, have been miſerably wrought upon for the keeping a vile, mean Subſiſtence, rather than Livelihood, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their Allegiance, and become Enemies to their Native Country: Some of whom have wantonly put themſelves on Board the Enemies Fleet, without Command or Office, purely out of appetite and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to rebel againſt their <hi>King,</hi> and to worry their Countrey: It is great pity theſe men ſhould not be taught by ſome exemplary brand, that their Allegiance is not circumſcribed within the four Seas; but that they have Obligations upon them of Duty and Loyalty towards the King, in what part of the world ſoever they ſhall inhabit.</p>
            <p>Their friends at home, impatient of longer delays for the ſucceſſes they had promiſed themſelves, and for the Succours which others had promiſed to ſend to them, made no doubt of doing the buſineſs themſelves, if they could appoint but a lucky day to begin the work; and you had heard of them in all places upon the third of the laſt moneth, their ſo much celebrated Third of <hi>September,</hi> if the great vigilance and indefatigable induſtry of the Good <hi>General,</hi> who is alwayes watchful for the Kings Safety, and the Peace of the Kingdom, had not two days before apprehended the Seditious Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and given Advertiſements for the ſecuring others in moſt parts of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> by the Confeſſions of many of whom their wicked Deſign is enough manifeſted and ready for Juſtice: Yet ſome of the Principal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are not yet taken, and ſome others got themſelves reſcued after they were apprehended.</p>
            <p>My Lords and Gentlemen, Let it not, I beſeech you, be ſaid of us, what was heretofore ſaid of the Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> when they were proſperous enough, and when they had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained greater Victories over their enemies abroad then we have done, <hi>Excellentibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentis citius defuit ars, qua Civem regant, quam qua hoſtem perdant;</hi> Let not theſe Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be kept warm in our boſoms till they ſting us to death. Let not thoſe who hate the Government, would deſtroy the Government, be ſheltred under the Shadow and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the Government. It is poſſible, and God knows it is but poſſible, that ſome men who are not friends to this or that part of the Government (for you are not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that they always diſcover what they are in truth moſt angry with) who would not buy theſe Alterations they moſt deſire, at the price of a Civill Warre; they would bring it fairly about, wait for a Godly Parliament, and do all by their conſent; Yet thoſe perſons muſt not take it ill that we cannot deſire they ſhould ever have it in their power to bring theſe Alterations to paſs by thoſe means they now ſeem to abhor: And I do heartily wiſh, I am ſure they will not be the worſe men, nor the worſe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject for it, that they would a little reflect upon what is paſt, remember how much they have once done, more then they intended to have done, nay, what they did heartily ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor the thought of doing; and they will then find the only way to preſerve themſelves innocent is to keep their minds from being vitiated by the firſt impreſſions, by Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, Murmurings and Repinings; and above all, by the converſation with thoſe men, or indulgence towards them, who would ſactifice the peace of the Kingdom to their own Ambition, Pride, and even to their Humour. If you carefully provide for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing your enemies at home, which will put you to little other expence then of Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Conſtancy and Circumſpection: You will find your enemies abroad leſs exalted, and in a ſhort time more inclined to live in Amity with you, then to make War upon you, eſpecially when they ſee you do <hi>in bell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pacis gerere negotium,</hi> and that you take the carrying on the War to heart, as the beſt and the only expedient to produce a happy and an honeſt Peace.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:174310:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
